<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../relaxng/schema4corpus.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <letter>
        <header> Letter from Marian Baldwin, June 30, 1917] On Board La Touraine, June 30th, 1917. </header>
        <body>
            <para> Even now that <setting>we are out of sight of land</setting>, it seems impossible
                that I am actually off to <country c="europe">France</country> and, for the first
                time in my life,<risk> traveling alone.</risk> Everything has happened so quickly
                    <risk>since the American Fund for French Wounded found an opening for me in
                        <city c="europe">Paris</city></risk> that I suppose I am still somewhat
                dazed and bewildered. The fact that I don't know what it will all be like and that I
                can't look ahead makes it easier to be happy and live in the present. Of course I
                have had a bit of a taste in <city c="u.s.">New York</city> of the work that the A.
                F. F. W. is doing but its Headquarters in <city c="europe">Paris</city> will be
                different in some ways I fancy. </para>
            <para> I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how few girls
                of my age are getting across, and<risk> I understood the grit and pluck which made
                    you encourage me on my great adventure and send me along a path which has proved
                    so dangerous of late.</risk>
            </para>
            <para>
                <setting>As we drifted down the river, in the sunset glow with two absurd tugs
                    puffing alongside,</setting> I know that many eyes were moist and that the same
                thought was in all our minds. How many of this ship's company will see that sky-line
                again! It was very quiet, no one spoke much, and, <setting>little by little, the
                    glow faded from the sky and one star after another appeared.</setting> I knew
                that <peace>you would be looking at those same stars down in <city c="u.s."
                        >Lakewood</city> and that your thoughts and prayers were the same that
                    filled my heart at that moment. Somehow distance does not separate, after all.
                </peace>
            </para>
            <para> We waited <setting>near the Statue of Liberty until midnight</setting>—a rumor
                had it that a "personage" was to come on board. This individual was shrouded in
                mystery until we put to sea when it was given out that the party which had clambered
                aboard in the night was none other than the Italian Mission. Our spirits rose at
                once for, what with Frank Sayre on the boat and <peace>these distinguished Italian
                    gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger convoy and so doubly
                    safe.</peace> However, <risk>thus far we have but two destroyers following
                    us.</risk>
                <setting>They can be seen distinctly outlined against the horizon, one on each side,
                    and seem to be the same somber gray which all ships are affecting in this
                    war.</setting> A sailor informed me this morning that we weren't in much danger
                for the first four or five days but that after that I might see some excitement.
                Here's hoping! </para>
            <para>
                <setting> I have a small inside cabin</setting> and my room-mate is quite a
                character. She is a native of <country>Haiti</country>, voluble and very
                    portly—<setting>has four large pieces of baggage in our tiny
                    stateroom,</setting> wears a costume which resembles a Mother Hubbard and smokes
                countless thin cigarettes that smell like incense! When I appeared, there didn't
                seem to be much room for me but, as she says, luckily I am small, and <setting>I was
                    soon tucked into the upper berth with my belongings!</setting><peace> She really
                    isn't bad and after looking me over carefully told me that she didn't think we
                    would fight and from that time has beamed upon me!</peace> She is going over to
                join her son who has been fighting with the French since the beginning of the war
                but will never go back to the Front now, having lost some fingers off each hand. She
                is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't lost more than his fingers. </para>
        </body>
        <footer>[Source: _Canteening Overseas_: 1917-1919, published 1920.]</footer>
    </letter>
    <letter>
        <header>July 8th, 1917</header>
        <body>
            <para>
                <risk>Friday night<setting> we entered the war zone</setting>
                </risk>at seven o'clock but you would never know it. Aside from boat-drills and
                sleeping on deck people act as usual. The officers on the boat are very particular
                about the drills; <risk>several times the alarm has sounded and we have been taught
                    just what to do in case we are hit</risk>. It's very funny to see the people
                rush below for their valuables, strapping on their life preservers as they go (which
                we always have near at hand wherever we are -on deck or in the saloon). In about
                five minutes we are lined up, divided into groups in front of our own particular
                life-boats which have been swung out over the sea ready to lower. Every one is
                checked off and each man is told what woman he is to save. (Great excitement at this
                point as no one of the men wants to save the lady detailed to him, but some one in
                another boat!) <risk>We all stand about looking too absurd and bumping into each
                    other's life preservers on the crowded upper deck.</risk> Finally the signal is
                given which releases us, and we all file down again to take off the clumsy heavy
                jackets of safety and regale ourselves with various amusements on the deck. </para>
            <para>
                <risk> Rumor has it that two ships have been sunk, one in the course ahead of where
                    we were</risk> yesterday and the other about an hour behind us. <risk>No one
                    knows how many lives were lost.</risk> Perhaps those three submarines were more
                fact than fiction after all. It is thought that we should make <city c="europe"
                    >Bordeaux</city> by Tuesday morning if all goes well and that the convoy which
                should have met us days ago will be with us to-night. <peace>This being Sunday, the
                    boys on board are very much dressed up, that is to say they are wearing clean
                    shirts and have their hair brushed!</peace>
                <peace><setting>It's a perfect day, warm and cloudless,</setting> and I've been
                    lying in the sun adding to my coat of tan. We all feel quite sad that the voyage
                    is so nearly over -it has been such loads of fun and I shall hate saying good-by
                    to every one. </peace>
            </para>
        </body>
        <footer>La Touraine</footer>
    </letter>
    <letter>
        <header>En route from Bordeaux to Paris, July 18th, 1917. </header>
        <body>
            <para> On landing yesterday I went straight to <setting>the Hôtel de France</setting>
                and it certainly was good to have room to turn around in: <peace>as for a bed with
                    real springs I greeted it with enthusiasm! Towards evening Frank and I took a
                    long walk about the city. A port town always interests me and we saw it all at
                    the loveliest time of day.</peace><setting> The harbor was full of fishing
                    smacks and small craft of all kinds</setting> and exquisite tones in the sails
                and rigging. <setting>The last rays of the sun cast a rosy hue over
                    everything</setting>, making one think at once of <city c="europe">Venice</city>
                and the days before the war. Later we wandered through some of the oldest parts of
                    <city c="europe">Bordeaux</city> and I really felt that I was abroad again! The
                    <setting>narrow winding streets and cobblestones, with here and there an ancient
                    façade or doorway and everywhere, in the poorest alleys, a bit of a vine or
                    potted plant in the windows</setting>.<peace> How do they manage to make it all
                    so picturesque and alluring?</peace>
            </para>
            <para> The women and the old men are doing everything and it is surprising to see the
                lady conductors. On this train they use women entirely, even in the dining car.
                    <peace>The war hasn't robbed them of vivacity or their beautiful complexions and
                    I believe they are even prettier in their simple black working clothes than
                    before.</peace>
            </para>
            <para>
                <peace> We are at present passing through the famous vineyards and I have never seen
                    the country look so beautiful.</peace>
                <setting>The crops seem in perfect condition</setting>, thanks to the patient labor
                of these wonderful women, and <setting>the grain waves in profusion</setting>
                everywhere. I have longed for you at every turn, how you would enjoy it
                        all.<peace><setting> The poppies are in their prime and, as the train whirls
                        by, they look like immense splashes of red</setting> -almost like stains of
                    blood against the gold of the wheat. </peace>
            </para>
            <para> I have just come in from a very excellent meal in the dining car<peace> -the food
                    was served promptly by two French girls of the peasant type and with a speed
                    that was wonderful, the car holding over thirty persons. </peace>
            </para>
        </body>
        <footer> Paris </footer>
    </letter>
</root>
