<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <meta>
        <title>Leaves</title>
        <author>Lloyd Schwartz</author>
        <date>- 1941-</date>
    </meta>
    <stanza>Every October it becomes <power>important, no, necessary to see the leaves
            turning,</power> to be surrounded by leaves turning; it's not just the symbolism,
            <power>to confront in the death of the year your death,</power>
        <descriptor h="nature">one blazing farewell appearance</descriptor>, though the irony isn't
        lost on you that <personification>nature is most seductive</personification> when it's about
        to die, <personification>flaunting the dazzle of its incipient exit</personification>, an
        ending that at least so far the effects of human progress <descriptor h="city">(pollution,
            acid rain)</descriptor> have not yet frightened you enough to make you believe is real;
        that is, you know this ending is a deception because of course nature is always renewing
        itself— the <personification>trees don't die, they just pretend,</personification>
        <descriptor h="nature">go out in style, and return in style</descriptor>: a new style. </stanza>
    <stanza>Is it deliberate how far they make you go especially if you live in the city to get far
        enough away from home to see not just trees but only trees? The <descriptor h="city">boring
            highways, roadsigns, high speeds, 10-axle trucks</descriptor>
        <personification>passing you as if they were in an even greater hurry than you to look at
            leaves</personification>: so you drive in terror for literal hours and it <descriptor
            h="nature">looks like rain, or snow, but it's probably just clouds</descriptor> (too
        cloudy to see any color?) and you wonder, given the poverty of your memory, which road had
        the most color last year, but it doesn't matter since <power>you're probably too late
            anyway, or too early— whichever road you take will be the wrong one and you've probably
            come all this way for nothing.</power>
    </stanza>
    <stanza>You'll be driving along depressed when suddenly a <descriptor h="nature">cloud will move
            and <personification>the sun will muscle through</personification> and ignite the
            hills</descriptor>. It may not last. Probably won't last. But for a moment
            <personification>the whole world comes to. Wakes up</personification>.
            <personification>Proves it lives</personification>. It lives— <descriptor h="nature"
            >red, yellow, orange, brown, russet, ocher, vermilion, gold. Flame and rust. Flame and
            rust, the permutations of burning</descriptor>. <power>You're on fire. Your eyes are on
            fire.</power> It won't last, you don't want it to last. You can't stand any more. But
        you don't want it to stop. It's what you've come for. It's what you'll come back for. It
        won't stay with you, but you'll remember that <power>it felt like nothing else you've felt
            or something you've felt that also didn't last.</power>
    </stanza>
    <meta>Copyright © 1992 by Lloyd Schwartz. From Goodnight, Gracie (The University of Chicago
        Press, 1992). Appears courtesy of the author.</meta>
</root>
